So in this lecture today we're going
to focus on reproducibility,
specifically reproducibility
as a research practice
and design constraint.
So in this course we're going to be
building pipelines doing things like
web data collection,
API, survey data processing,
databases, looking at
record linkages, etc.
So a common thread is that these
pipelines involve many decisions in
many moving parts.
One is the discipline that makes
these decisions visible and these
moving parts vulnerable.
So today we're going
to cover three layers.
First, what reproducibility is and
how it relates to
replication crisis.
Second, why multiple comparisons and
specification search matter, even
when you're using strong
designs like natural experiments.
And third, we're going to run some
practical tooling, environment
capture, Git workflows,
containers, and what it means to
produce a research artifact.
Reproducibility asks a simple
question, can someone else obtain
the same result, using
the same data and code without
informal guidance?
So that last phrase, without
informal guidance, is the key.
If your research works only if you
sit next to someone and explain
which files to run,
which settings to flip, and which
versions to install,
then it's not reproducible.
And reproducibility is the minimum
standard for credible research.
It doesn't guarantee the claim is
true, but it guarantees
the claim is inspectable.
So in this course, I want you to
treat reproducibility not as a
polishing step at the end, but as
a design choice from the beginning.
If you build reproducibility in
early, everything becomes easier.
Collaboration, debugging,
validation, and future reuse.
So now let's connect this to the
replication process.
Across the social science and
behavioral sciences, many published
findings fail to replicate,
effects such as shrink or disappear,
and results depend
on analytic choices.
So the key line is, this is not
about fraud, it's about systems.
So what does that mean?
It means that incentives, workflows,
and publication norms can produce a
world where gradual findings
can revive.
It's not that most researchers are
dishonest, it's that researchers
have degrees of freedom,
journal select for novelty, and many
results are underpowered or
sensitive to choices.
So reproducibility is part of the
responses because it
makes analytic choices visible
and our results checkable.
So this slide lists some common
contributors, research degrees of
freedom, small sample
sizes, noisy estimates, selective
reporting, and multiple
high-bombs of the testing.
So a useful way to think about this
is, many failures are not
errors, they're outcomes
of flexibility.
So if a researcher can reasonably
choose among many modeling
decisions, then some specifications
will produce
significant results by chance.
If only those are reported, the
publication record becomes biased
towards false positives.
That's why replication efforts often
find smaller effects.
The original literature contains a
selection mechanism.
So the big lesson here is, good
research practice is not only about
better models, it's about
constraining flexibility, making
choices transparent, and evaluating
robustness honestly.
So there's two kind of other key
points that I want to
relate into this lecture.
So the first is, we spent a lot of
time in social science research and
many form classes
talking about p-hacking as a
resource problem.
And often, p-hacking is nefarious.
There's a second problem that is
discussed most often, and
it's this idea called the
Garden of Orch-ing Path.
It's popularized by Andrew Bellman.
And it's the idea that small
decision rules that go into
transforming your data for analysis
can have really large
effects on your outcome.
So the example that's often used is,
let's say you want to evaluate the
effect of a novel
drug on some sort of health outcome,
and you think that there's a
different effect by age
over time.
So then to carry out your analysis,
let's say you want to
decide, how do I treat age
as a predictor in my model?
Maybe you do something like begin to
binary variable for
someone who's younger than 18
versus older age than 18.
Maybe you do it into categorical
outcomes from 18 and
younger, 19 to 25, 26 to 30,
et cetera.
Or maybe you treat it as a
continuous variable, or maybe you do
something like have a polynomial
order in there.
Any of these decision rules are
defensible on their own, but they
can also then have
an effect on your outcome of
interest if you're interacting with
your treatment variable there.
So this idea of gardening for gene
paths is that we make
these honest decisions when
we're transforming your data for
analysis, and it can end up having
these profound effects
on our analysis where they don't end
up replicating because of some
decision rules that a researcher
made, even if they
weren't at their age start.
So the idea of
gardening for gene paths.
The second idea that I often think
of when I'm going through
replication crises or thinking
about researchers is this kind of
joke, the infinite monkey theorem,
where if we had an
infinite amount of time, an infinite
amount of monkeys working on
different typewriters,
they would reproduce all the
published work of Shakespeare.
So it's this idea that by random
chance, with an infinite amount of
time, monkeys could
create all these masterpieces.
How does this relate
to academic research?
So often I think of it in terms of
there's thousands of
researchers trying to answer
some more questions.
We're all sitting at our computers.
We're all collecting data at the
same time, and we're running
regressions at the same
time.
And let's say that our threshold for
a type 1 error is 0.05, right?
Or rather, let's say we're all
running our regressions at a time.
Let's say our type 1 error rate is
0.05, or 95% confidence intervals.
We maybe end up just by chance
having 20 different researchers
looking at the same type of outcome.
One of them finds a false positive
or has a type 1 error.
That order comes from getting
published because it's
much more interesting.
There's nothing
nefarious in that case.
Or if we have all these researchers
working at the same time on the same
question as collecting
data, that person maybe
didn't do anything wrong.
It's just they had a sample that
ended up producing an outcome that
was very interesting.
So two kinds of key ideas for
replication, for own work in the
replication crisis.
P-hacking is definitely a problem.
But we can also think about things
like the garden of 14
pounds and the infinite monkey
theorem.
So multiple comparisons matter
because many studies implicitly test
multiple outcomes,
multiple specifications, and
multiple subgroups.
So even with a single natural
experiment, false positives
accumulate at that fraction.
So let's make this intuitive.
Suppose you have a policy shock and
you test 10 outcomes.
Even if the policy has no true
effect on the outcome, you should
expect some low P-values
just by chance.
So suppose alternatively that you
estimate the same effect under a
range of control sets
in Windows.
These combinations produce
significant results by law.
So multiplicity is not only an issue
in exploratory work, it's a
structural issue in empirical
practice.
So as a course take away for this is
if your pipeline implicitly
encourages many tests,
you need a plan for how you will
interpret them, adjust them, do
pre-specifications,
or try to do at a
minimum transparently.
So this slide is specifically about
why multiplicity shows up even when
you think your design is
strong.
Natural experiments often involve
many outcomes for treatment, events
to any coefficients
over time, and sensitivity across
Windows and controls.
So event studies
are a great example.
An event study is not one estimate,
it's a path of estimates.
We have multiple coefficients, each
in separate hypotheses.
You look at the path and visually
interpreting it without adjustment
can lead to overconfidence.
So another example is bandwidth
sensitivity in RDD designs.
So we have different bandwidth that
can yield different estimates.
And people may choose one that looks
right or is significant.
So multiplicity is
structural, not accidental.
It comes to the fact that robust
inference often
requires checking many angles.
And the moment you check many
angles, you can have
potential false positives.
The lesson is
never check robustness.
The lesson is to recognize that
robustness checks themselves can
become a search process
if you don't discipline them.
So this slide is the risk scenario,
trying alternative
controls, varying bandwidths or
cutoffs or exploring
subgroups post-hoc.
So without discipline, robustness
becomes overfitting.
Overfitting here doesn't mean
machine learning overfitting.
It means that you're fitting your
narrative to the combination of
choices that yields
the most compelling results.
So this is one reason why
transparent workflows matter.
If the full specification path is
visible, what was tried, what was
discarded, then readers
can assess whether the result is
robust or selective.
So this also motivates tools like
pre-registration, multiverse
analysis, and systematic robustness
reporting.
You don't have to adopt all those in
every project, but you should
understand why the
problem exists.
So what does
replication really test?
Replication evaluates data access,
code, executeability, analytic
transparency, and sensitivity to
assumptions.
We have exact numerical equality and
it's for--exact
numerical equality is fairly the
point.
Line matters because in
computational pipelines, exact
equality is often too strict.
Floating point differences,
parallelization, random seeds, and
version drift can produce
slightly different numbers.
So the deeper point is whether the
qualitative conclusions hold and
where the analytic pipeline
can be rerun and inspected.
So when we talk about replication,
it's helpful to separate.
We have
computational reproducibility.
Can I run your code
and get your results?
Replication of results to get the
same substantive conclusions when we
implement the same method
and robustness generalization.
Does the conclusion hold under
reasonable
variations or new samples?
So this lecture is going to focus
most on computational
reproducibility and research
artifacts because these are the
prerequisites for the other two.
So even with shared code and data,
results can differ across
machines, library versions
change behavior, and randomness is
handled differently.
This is one of the most
underestimated
problems in graduate training.
People assume code is deterministic.
In practice, it often isn't.
So for randomness, if you don't fix
seeds, models can
differ across runs.
Even with seeds, some libraries use
non-deterministic kernels.
This is especially a problem in
machine learning
and network science.
Then we also have library behavior.
So default
settings change over time.
A function that used to sort one way
may sort another way.
And then a model fitting function
may change an optimizer.
So computation is part
of the research design.
If your pipeline depends on defaults
you didn't specify, then your
pipeline is fragile.
So operating systems can also affect
your applications.
Results can vary across Linux, Mac,
Windows, file system behavior,
floating point implementations,
and path handle.
This is where a practical
collaboration pain comes from.
A script that uses a Windows-style
file path breaks on Linux.
A file name that differs only in
capitalization can behave
differently across file systems.
So inline endings can differ.
Some compile
dependencies behave differently.
So assuming identical
environments is unsafe.
The takeaway is, if you want to work
to be reproducible across machines,
you must treat the execution
environment as part of the project.
That includes path conventions,
dependency management,
and explicit instructions.
So over time, R and Python packages
updates, default behaviors change,
and deprecated
functions break pipelines.
Code that ran once
may not run again.
This is why I put my code on GitHub
is not the same as my
results for reproducible.
If you don't capture versions, your
collaborator might
install a newer package version
and get a different result.
The script may fail entirely.
So the habit is treat dependency
versions as part of your project.
So the best practice includes
explicit package versions.
We have locked files like R, Rn, and
R, and requirement.txt,
or a locked file in Python and
minimal system dependencies.
Environments must be
specified, not inferred.
So this is a key idea.
Don't rely on the reader to guess
your environment,
making it explicit
and easy to recreate.
So in practical course terms, this
is why we care about
requirements as a text file or a
locked file in Python.
R environment lock in R and
potential container definitions.
The goal is not perfection.
The goal is that someone can run
your pipeline without
heroic troubleshooting.
So what is Git as a scientific tool?
Git supports version code histories,
branching and experimentation,
and transferring collaboration.
So Git records how results evolved.
This is a major shift
from files on my laptop.
Git creates a history of changes.
That history is part of the
scientific transparency.
It also supports collaboration.
You can propose changes via branches
and pull requests,
review them, and merge
them in a controlled way.
So in this course, we treat Git as
part of the
scientific instrumentation,
not as a bureaucratic hurdle.
In Git Hub, we have commits.
So each commit should
represent a logical change.
It should be reversible and it
should be interpretable.
So our commit history
is our research law.
There's a practical way to think
about the discipline.
A clean commit history makes your
project easier to debug,
easier to audit,
and easier to explain.
So the useful here is that a commit message should tell you
what
you want to do. The useful here is that a commit
message should tell
you what changed and why,
not in a verbose way, just enough to
understand the intent.
So in the same way that a lab
notebook reports experiments,
your commit history should report an
analytic evolution.
So containers handle
bung and dependencies,
isolate execution environments, and
improve portability.
So they reduce but may
not eliminate variability.
The key point is reduce here.
Containers help because they
standardize the environment,
operating system, libraries,
dependency versions,
and system packages.
But containers
don't solve everything.
They don't guarantee identical
hardware and they don't solve
conceptual errors.
But still for reproducible pipeline,
containers are often the closest
thing we have to run anywhere.
So I want to emphasize that
containers are not magic.
They do not fix data errors,
conceptual mistakes,
or poor documentation.
They address
execution, not inference.
This is a crucial clarification.
If your data are biased, a container
reproduces the bias.
If your model is misspecified, a
container reproduces
the mis-squefaction.
If your readme is unclear, a
container doesn't
explain what to run.
So containers are tools, not a
substitute for method.
[silence]
So a reproducible project produces
data, code, documentation, and
execution instructions.
The artifact is the contribution.
So this is a core course value.
If you build a
high-quality data product,
cleanly collected,
well-documented, validated,
with a pipeline that
others can then run,
the artifact itself is a
scholarly contribution.
And increasingly, that is how
serious research is evaluated.
Not only are results by the quality
and the reuse potential of the
underlying data and code.
[silence]
So reproducibility requires clear
readme, data proven,
known limitations, and
explicit assumptions.
So undocumented
pipelines are not reproducible.
So this is the soft part
of what's actually hard.
Documentation is the bridge between
your mental model
and someone else's
ability to run your work.
So a good readme will
answer what are the data,
how they are
attained and accessed them,
how to run the pipeline end-to-end,
what outputs are produced, and what
limitations are known.
So in this course, we're going to
treat documentation as
part of the pipeline,
not as an optional polish.
[silence]
So let me summarize the four
takeaways in this lecture.
Treat reproducibility and design,
build it in early.
Anticipate multiplicity, recognize
where multiple
comparisons and specifications
search arise, especially in natural
experiment settings.
You want to capture
environment early,
so you want to lock your versions,
minimize your
dependencies, and make reruns possible.
You want to make
artifacts usable by others.
Goal is that someone else can run
your project with minimal friction.
[silence]
And if you do these four things, you
will produce work that is
easier to collaborate on,
easier to validate, and
much easier to defend.
So a few key discussion ideas to
keep in your mind
during today's session.
So what kind of results
are hardest to reproduce?
Is it models with non-determinism,
pipelines with many dependencies,
or results that depend
on specific versions?
Where does
multiplicity enter your work?
Is it multiple outcomes, multiple
specifications, or
repeated rebusses checks?
And what is the minimal
reproducible artifact?
If you had to hand your
project to someone else,
what would they need
to rerun it to trust it?
[silence]